hello everybody
how's it going tabard how's it going
Seth how are you
really good thank you
I'm really looking forward to this
conversation that we're going to have
today I think this is a really important
topic uh and I know that you guys are a
wealth of knowledge and information on
this topic so I'm really looking forward
to it uh for everyone else just give us
a few moments while we get a few of the
speakers up on stage and as we get the
room all sorted out and then looking
forward to diving into this conversation
all right so it's about is there anyone
else that we're waiting for right now or
uh do we want to start brief
introductions and kind of the topic at
hand
I think that is here also as a speaker
I see Rafe
Gustavo is free to join as well Groove
uh but yeah we can get started yeah so
uh why don't we just start with
introductions for everyone on the stage
uh well so we'll go around and then uh
after that we'll kind of dive into
things
yeah sounds good I'll jump in I guess so
I'm a Tebow Tim on Twitter uh recent
contributor to Wasabi wallet working on
many different things I'm excited for
this uh this space is going to be a good
one
hey everybody I'm Seth or Seth for
privacy I'm head of content at
foundation and have a focus on bitcoin
privacy with the education I've done the
past and what I'm working on now um so
it's kind of where I'm coming from
oh I'm maxillou brand uh I'm also
privacy Advocate open source lover and
have been contributing to Wasabi for a
couple years now
um in the meantime I'm the CEO of CK
snacks which is the coordinator uh that
that is well The Conjuring coordinator
and we're sponsoring a bunch of
contributors to a Sally wallet
hey guys
um I'm Rafe I'm also a long-term
contributor for Wasabi wallet and
generally very interested in all these
like privacy related
projects
and yeah very excited too see how this
discussion goes today
I feel a little outnumbered here on the
uh only non-wasabi wallet connected
person so yeah I know man I invited the
samurai wallet tdev and and Lohan but
they couldn't make it so maybe another
time
it's good that you know we're actually
having this debate
yeah I'm glad if you want to do an
introduction real quick and then we'll
uh get into the topic at hand
hi guys I'm Vlad and I'm such a privacy
guy that I had my permissions not
allowed to access my microphone so I had
to close the call and then enable my
phone to access my microphone get back
raise my hand so thank you for having me
I do the Bitcoin takeover podcast I also
do the BTC tkbr Open Source magazine
which you can download and print for
free and some people call me a Wasabi
Phil but I've been a user since early
2019 and I've been constantly watching
the project grow and improve I like what
it's doing I want to give credit to
Yuval kogman for Designing the wabi-sabi
protocol because we're gonna talk about
about a lot about what he has created
and yeah that's pretty much it
awesome thank you for the intro to uh
introductions everyone uh Tebow maybe
I'll kick it over to you to start things
off uh I know that this is probably one
of the more technical rooms but uh if
you want to just give a brief overview
of what a coin join is and then uh after
that kind of a breakdown of what toxic
changes and we can kind of get into the
questions and uh some of the articles
that you guys have written
yeah sure
so I guess before talking about corn
join I'll talk about a brief like intro
on bitcoin transactions because it's
always at least one input that is
consumed and one output that is created
right that uh transaction output is the
tx0 and when it's unspent and ready to
be spent we call it the utxo so the
unspent transaction output and
um of course on bitcoin the sum of all
the current utxos they give you the
circulating supply of all the Bitcoin at
any given time anybody can verify this
running full node this is great but it
has some privacy trade-offs right and
this is the core of Bitcoin which relies
on the utxo model and so in reality if
you send let's say you have one BTC utxo
you want to send 0.3 BTC you're going to
send the entire 1btc utxo and you're
gonna get 0.7 BTC back as change right
and that change output is traceable
it is hard to manage to avoid leaking
some personal information
and this is why it's called toxic change
because it is in a way it can use like a
more fancier parlance it's
deterministically linked to the original
input of the transaction
so quantums can help you reclaim your
privacy and deal with the problem of
toxic change
um coin join what is it well it's a
collaborative Bitcoin transaction so in
some cases it allows many participants
sometimes hundreds in the case of
wabi-sabi to send Bitcoin together in
one single transaction
and so conjoin in that sense it helps
you hide your transaction history and it
makes it very hard to track the foes of
funds and so the connection between the
input and output of a transaction is
broken and so all of a sudden you are
yes what we call fungible utxos so those
utxos those unspent transaction outputs
they're not distinguishable from each
other
and that's why coin joints are so
interesting from a privacy standpoint
however the problem of toxic change is
not entirely gone from coin joints and
so
today you have three major
implementations who have different
strategies to deal with coin joints
namely join Market
um then you have Whirlpool those two
rely on zero link
protocol which is a coin joint design
and we'll we'll talk about this later
I'm pretty sure
and then wabi-sabi which uses a
different uh sorry Wasabi wallet 2.0
which uses the wabi-sabi conjoin
protocol which is a completely revamped
design from zero link protocol and again
we'll talk about the differences I'm
sure a bit later I don't want to
overwhelm everybody
and so so yeah I think it should be
really interesting to discuss the
different strategies by which these
conjun implementation actually handle
toxic change
um whether you know they included in
coin joins isolated from coin joins or
outright eliminated and what it means
for privacy and for users
and maybe to add some small things about
the basics of coin join
um what we're trying to avoid is to leak
the input to input linkage as well as
the output to Output linkage and the
input to Output linkage so these are
kind of the three things that we want to
hide input to input linkage is also
known as the common input ownership
heuristic and so if you're making a
transaction by yourself which most
people are you can select multiple coins
to be spent in the same transaction on
the input side and then in adversary who
looks at this transaction on the
blockchain can say that I assume every
input belongs to the same person so we
just assume that input to input linkage
is linked to the same person
um now a coin drone is by definition a
collaborative Bitcoin transaction with
multiple users owning multiple inputs in
this transaction so we literally break
the common input ownership heuristic
meaning we have that potential to break
the link on the input to input side so
all of a sudden we no longer know how
many inputs one person entered here or
which inputs belong to the same person
and likewise on on the output side it
would be preferable to to not find out
that these two outputs belong to the
same person
and notice that this is you know this is
different like being able to Cluster
just the inputs you might be able to do
that without finding out which outputs
that person got or you could for example
just cluster on the output side but not
being able to find out what what's up on
the input like which users which inputs
belong to that same users
yeah no I think there's some great stuff
does anyone want to add anything else
before we jump into the three different
types or the three main ways that it
currently exists for dealing with the
toxic change
not necessarily adding anything but uh
just uh for the listeners out there
there are some resources some tweets
being pinned in the Twitter space right
now where we shared some threads about
these strategies so if you wanna
read about them at the same time feel
free to check them out yeah definitely
and uh yeah Tebow I think uh or anyone
can take this so basically as you were
mentioning there's kind of three ways
that it currently exists so there is the
inclusion of the change in the coin join
there's the isolation of the change
before the coin join and then there's
the elimination of the change in the
coin join so that's kind of uh as you
mentioned before there's kind of the
three main implementations of Wasabi
joint Market Samurai and wasabi kind of
has two factions it has Wasabi 1.0 and
wasabi 2.0 um yeah if you want to break
it down or if anyone wants to talk about
those in parallel those three different
uh distinctions of how the toxic change
is dealt with
I I guess let me uh be the joint Market
guy which is also project I love him to
contribute to
um so in joint Market we have a maker
and taker architecture the taker is the
coin join coordinator meaning if the
taker is a user who brings together the
inputs and outputs of different users
and writes them well into the same
transaction
and the taker especially can can set the
round parameters meaning how many inputs
should be there or how many makers
should be there as well as very
importantly what is the equal value
output amount so in the joint Market
transaction there is going to be one
output denomination let's say 0.2
Bitcoin
and those 0.2 Bitcoin will be like 10
times on the output side so 10 outputs
worth 0.2 Bitcoin
um and the taker gets to choose what is
this equal amount denomination
um and then the taker you know says okay
cool I want to make this new transaction
and I want to invite acres to add their
inputs to this transaction so the taker
talks to the makers who advertise
publicly hey I'm willing to coin join
for any amount right let's say between
0.1 Bitcoin and one Bitcoin I'm happy to
coin join anything uh the 0.2 Bitcoin is
within the range so the taker will will
talk to the maker and say hey please add
your inputs let's say the taker then
adds a 0.3 Bitcoin input uh sorry the
maker answer 0.3 Bitcoin input so he
receives the 0.2 Bitcoin equal amount
the private output as well as the 0.1
Bitcoin change
uh in fact it will actually be 0.11 or
something like this because the maker
gets paid a small fee uh by the taker
right so the taker is inviting makers
into his own transactions and why would
makers ever join the transaction of the
taker or because he bribes them he gives
them money that's a good way to convince
people to do what you want
um but also important to note the taker
pays for the mining fee of all the
makers and so makers can earn
effectively money like they they don't
have to pay for the mining fee and they
do get a liquidity free from the taker
um but this means that so because the
taker dictates I want to have 0.2 on the
output side
basically no maker is going to have the
exactly right amount on the input side
right so most likely the maker will add
more money on the input side than the
equal denomination and not exactly that
amount which means if you have more
money than the standard amount you will
have the change of amount which will be
given to you in the change output and
this change output can be tied to the
input sum so let's say if the maker
added two inputs
um
then we can see that these two inputs
minus the equal amount so the private
output amount equals the the change
output so here we can have an input to
Output linkage
including an input to input linkage so
because of that change amount we can say
that these two inputs pretty surely
belong to the same maker so we have an
input to input linkage and an input to
Output linkage so these two inputs have
paid for this change output
yeah thanks for that Max uh Seth I see
your hand up uh yeah if there's anything
you want to comment or if I was going to
say if you want to also denote and talk
about the the samurai implementation or
the whirlpool implementation that'd be
great
yeah yeah I figured I'd jump in and
handle the the samurai side of things
um so when you look at Samurai wallet
the approach that's taken to preventing
a user from harming themselves with this
toxic change
um is to isolate that toxic change so
Tebow went into it well on his his
article
um but essentially what happens is when
you go to gain privacy through Samurai
wallet you use their coin drone protocol
called whirlpool and Whirlpool has a set
of denomination pools so essentially
when you join funds you go and bring
them in you want to gain privacy those
funds have to get broken down into the
correct denominations for whatever coin
join pool you want to use that can be
0.5 b2c 0.05 0.1.01 there are multiple
denominations when you do that what
happens is you do an initial transaction
that essentially preps your input for
going through the coin join round which
is called the tx0 and so that takes
whatever your inputs are breaks them up
into the right denominations so let's
say you have
uh one BTC and you want to mix in the
0.05 BTC pool it'll break down year one
BTC input into all of those 0.05 BDC
outputs and then you'll have the amount
necessary to pay for fees in those
outputs as well and then you'll have
that change output which we've we've
been referring to as toxic change and
the reason we call it toxic change just
to harp on that point a little bit more
is that that change gains no anonymity
or privacy through mixing and
essentially that change links directly
back to the wallet that entered that
mixing round and so if you use that
change especially if you combine it with
other toxic change or if you combine it
with funds that have already been mixed
and you're trying to spend you are
revealing that you are the same person
whenever you do that
um but the approach that Samurai wallet
does is they isolate that change they
set it aside in a separate account that
you cannot easily spend from
intentionally so that you can't use that
toxic change on accident and harm your
privacy on the on the other side and so
that your inputs when you're mixing are
exactly what you need there's no change
coming out of the mixing round itself
you get exact denominations no change to
worry about but that doesn't mean that
you have that this toxic change that you
then have to deal with later uh and
there's kind of three main approaches
one is if it's a small amount that you
can't mix in a like a smaller Whirlpool
denomination you could either just sit
on it and not worry about it and just
wait for maybe a better privacy
technology to come along in the future
or you could take it you could swap it
for something like Panero on an instant
exchange to just be able to have some
way to spend those funds moving forward
or if it is a large enough amount you
can continue to mix down into smaller
pools within Whirlpool until you're left
with just a very small change output
because eventually at some point it's
not a spendable amount and so you'll
just be harming your privacy if you try
to combine that with anything else
um so those are kind of the core
approaches and make sure that the heart
the user can't unintentionally harm
themselves by spending that toxic change
but it does take that extra prep
transaction called the dx0 on the input
side but that does guarantee that in the
actual coin join transaction there's no
change there's no toxic linkage there's
no deterministic links so it's a
powerful approach but it isn't
necessarily the most block space
efficient approach
yeah thanks for that Seth uh Tebow do
you want to go through Wasabi 1.0 and
wasabi 2.0 I know they're kind of
different in the way that they handle
them
yeah I mean I'd love to but I think uh
Max hillebrand on this call is more
suited for that he's been working on it
for years yeah uh I guess I was open
enough for a Tebow or anyone else that
wants to take it go ahead Max
okay
um so Wasabi 1.0 uh includes the change
directly into the coin join which is
similar to join Market
um however there's some important
differences compared to join Market
there is no maker and taker
differentiation like the end user is not
the coin join coordinator the coin drone
coordinator is a third party and this
coin join coordinator does not have
inputs on the in this coin join and so
technically he's not a participant of
the coin join
um and uh so however still that
coordinator similar to to Samurai uh it
dictates the round the the equal
denominations for this round
um and in the Wasabi case we started out
uh with 0.1 being the only standard
denomination or equal denomination uh in
a coin join round uh so very similar to
join market right so we have one a bunch
of inputs and then one equal amount that
multiple outputs have plus a bunch of
change coins and here again if you have
registered multiple inputs uh then an
outside Observer can can look at the
change Value Plus the equal denomination
and see which input sums uh go to yeah
sum up to this and that can lead to
revealing the common input ownership and
again the common the inputs to Output
linkage to the change output right so
the uh the standard or the equal amount
is private but the change output can be
linked to the input
and the way Wasabi 1.0 dealt with it uh
is uh well so it was sent to the same
account derivation path Wasabi only uses
one deprivation path uh and not multiple
accounts uh however in the user
interface it was denoted with a big red
shield thing and on set one a
non-private coin uh contrarily to the
equal denominations which had an
anonymity set let's say 50 and a green
shield associated with it and when you
spend uh you know you would either
select only all the private coins by by
default
um and if you would if you were to
select private non-private coins there
there is a warning displayed
um well ultimately this this does
require some knowledge of of the Bitcoin
utxo model and and coin selection is all
notoriously difficult so this was a big
point of friction in in wasabi 1.0 in
addition that we did I believe with
Wasabi 1.1 was a multi-round sorry a
multi-denomination round uh so uh this
was actually an idea that was uh brought
to light by Yuval nothing much uh that
that Vlad mentioned earlier
um uh so here kind of his early ideas
came came out about adding multiple
equal denominations uh so we had 0.1 0.2
0.4 0.8 uh 1.6 3.2 and so on so always
doubling an exponential series of equal
denominations
um another important note is that every
round this equal denomination was
slightly adjusted it was never exactly
0.1 it was a range between like 0.11 and
0.9
um and with every subsequent round the
equal denomination was slightly lower
this was to ensure that at least one
person did not receive a change output
so basically the poorest guy didn't pay
any fees and got didn't get a change
output
um and that yeah that removed the need
for change for at least one person but
it had a lot of other weird downsides
especially that then yeah I can explain
later how we improved on that with with
2.0
um
so
yes uh
I think in regards to 1.0 that is about
everything that did I miss anything
well Max there's also something to be
said about the fact that you could see
both utxos in your wallet and even if
they were marked with different colors
you could try to consolidate them but
you would get this warning message that
it's a bad idea but in practice if you
ignored the message you could make this
mistake which basically defeats the
purpose of a coin join and I guess this
is a very important situation which led
to the optimizations that U-Haul has
made in the wabi-sabi protocol
because I guess part of the criticism
for Wasabi 1.0 was that newbies were
making consolidations that led to
mistakes that basically defeated the
purpose of a coin join
yes exactly the user experience was a
bit clunky that that was the main uh the
main issue I think that the community
had for uh for 1.0
um and yeah it was basically a burden
that was passed on the user as Max said
you had to be aware of the utxo model
how to do coin control properly how to
properly label your etxo and so on so
forth which of course adds complexity to
the to the overall ux I think Rafe had
some points also to make on the 1.0 and
2.0 distinction
uh yeah thanks so you know like all of
these three coin joint implementations
that we now talked about they are
basically like zero like a zero link
based and they all seem to have this
like same problems uh even though they
have a little bit of like different
implementation but they all have these
same problems so if you have a certain
denomination no matter what it is
you're not gonna necessarily be able to
um like you're very likely not going to
have exactly that amount when you go
into that coin joint so you either will
have to consolidate multiple inputs
together revealing the common input
heuristic or the ownership which is bad
for your privacy and also if you don't
have exactly the uh the right amount you
will have like you can have some extra
and you will have then the toxic change
like these were basically the problems
that all of these three coin joint
implementations had
and there's different ways of kind of
handling then the toxic change and
everything but what we try to do with
2.0 is kind of acknowledge these
problems and we try to do like totally
different kind of approach approach
trying to actually solve some of the
problems like for example
um like whatever the denomination you
have and you know like the the fact that
you're gonna have to consolidate
multiple smaller inputs together to be
able to participate in it like that is
something that we really really had to
fix and there is no really way around it
so that's kind of like where we started
thinking about 2.0 and how it got built
up but I think Max is the right person
to explain that one
um I would maybe preface it with uh the
the question of what does an outside
Observer know and what does the
coordinator know and that is different
for for each of these implementations
for example in join Market the
coordinator the taker knows everything
he knows which inputs come from which
maker and which outputs including the
equal amount private output the taker
can link it to each maker
um and so there's no blinding in the
coin drawing coordination happening
which is why I would not call join
Market zero link by the way the zero
link paper was outlining a specific
application of the charmian blind
signature
um ecash protocol to ensure that the
coordinator does not learn uh the
linkage of inputs to outputs that
there's zero link on input to Output
against the coordinator as an adversary
and this is achieved by utilizing well
basically ecash as Anonymous access
rights token so you you get an access
right token when you register an input
that used to be a German blind signature
and then if you want to register an
output you have to present or to spend
this ecash token back to the coordinator
and the coordinator allows only outputs
that are registered if they present this
ecash credential and because these ecash
credentials are perfectly private like
100 theoretically perfect Anonymous with
the anonymity set of all users in this
in this round we have great privacy and
the coordinator cannot link inputs to
outputs as much as any outside Observer
right so the coordinator does not have
any additional information
um however there's there's problems here
um with what we used uh old idea from
Gregory Maxwell in 2013 Charming blind
signatures uh the value of the ecash
token uh basically depends on the on the
private key that signed it
um so if you have a an equal amount of
0.1 Bitcoin you have one private key
that signs the e-cash tokens that allow
the people to register the 0.1 Bitcoin
output
but then if you have the 0.2 Bitcoin
denomination that's a different private
key okay so each denomination is is a
separate part of privacy so to say
within one non-domination you're
perfectly private but the coordinator is
sure that a 0.1 token is very different
from a 0.2 token and so the amount of
the token is public knowledge
um and and that or acknowledge to the
coordinator I guess
um and so this leads to problems
um for example that you can only have a
limited amount of denominations because
if you would want to have uh like a a
unique key for for each Satoshi amount
where you would have millions of
billions of different private Keys
needed to represent each of these
denominations
um and that's not just computationally
expensive and bandwidth expensive that
also decreases your privacy right
because remember that there's no privacy
across pools across different private
keys so if you're the only one that
registered exactly
0.1234567 Bitcoin all your anonymity set
is one and the coordinator can again
link your activity
so that's a problem
um and that's by the way why Samurai
choose to have the tx0 transaction so
that you prepare your input amount to be
exactly that value that you need so that
you can with one single private key with
one single standard denomination you
could you can make the coin join and you
prepare your input so that you have a
one input one output part in that coin
join transaction with just one private
key that does the Charming and blind
signatures
um and well it's so the the reason why
coin joins especially Samurai and wasabi
1.0 uh have this single standard
denomination model and why everyone was
thinking about it for in the past was
because of these strong and blind
signatures
um and well
we realized that with having this
limited cryptography where the value of
the ecash token is is known we just can
never get rid of of the change problem
it will always be there and so we set
out in in the Wasabi research Club
um to find a better cryptography that
allows us to coordinate those coin
joints better
uh and we stumbled upon this well Fringe
cryptography paper
um that introduced keyed verified
Anonymous credentials uh which for all
intents and purpose is a blind signature
just like charmian uh or or uh snorer
blind signatures
um and what we introduced on top of that
is a homomorphic value encryption and
Patterson commitment uh quite similar to
what Monero uses or the liquid sidechain
which basically hides the amount of of
something in the monero's case it hides
the amount of the inputs and outputs and
then the wabi-sabi case it hides the
amount of the ecash credential meaning
now the coordinator just has one single
private key so to say and he can create
these credentials but the value of the
credential is completely unknown
um so it is between 5000 satoshis and 40
000 Bitcoin
um and that that new ecash system allows
us to coordinate coin joints with
arbitrary amounts uh privately
um I I see that Seth has his hand up so
before I continue this enormous rant
please go ahead
I would say go ahead and finish up I
just I have some some questions that I'd
love to get clarified around wabi-sabi
itself so I'll let you let you wrap up
and I can jump in with some questions
okay cool uh thanks so now we have this
new Anonymous ecash system that that has
Anonymous amounts meaning null you can
register an arbitrary amount input
um
0.12345 Bitcoin right and you get an
e-cash credential that's worth exactly
the amount of one single input
and so you no longer have to combine
multiple inputs to get a credential
um as to some extent is with uh Samurai
because of the tx0 there you have to
combine multiple inputs to to get your
standard denominations and with Wasabi
you have to do that too right if you
have less than 0.1 Bitcoin which is the
smallest standard denomination you have
to consolidate multiple inputs up to
seven inputs to be able to get that
amount with wabi-sabi or Wasabi 2.0 you
can register each input regardless of
what value it has you can register it by
itself and get these Anonymous amount
credentials and you have the anonymity
set of all the users in the round
um regardless of what denomination they
have so different to these strongly
blind signatures
um and then later in in output
registration because you have these
Anonymous uh ecash tokens you can change
the amount of them right so let's say
you register a 0.123 input so you get an
e-cash credential worth 0.123 you can
split it up into let's say three
credentials point one point
o two and 0.03 or whatever and uh now
you have a new set of credentials with
arbitrary values that you have chosen
and later in output registration you can
present each of these credentials
separately under a new tour identity to
register each of your outputs so both
your inputs and your outputs are
registered completely separately with a
unique tour identity and with a new
ecash credential that is not tied to
your other inputs or outputs or the
inputs and outputs from other users
um so this enables you to register in
the coin join any amount of inputs that
you want without the coordinator
learning that these belong to the same
person and any amount of outputs that
you want with arbitrary values
um and this means the coordinator no
longer dictates to you about the
denominations or the number of inputs
that you're allowed to do
um the coordinator is a lot more
hands-off a lot more complexity is on
the client side the client the Wasabi
2.0 client your wallet on desktop got a
lot more smarter with this upgrade
um because now we can be flexible about
how many inputs do I register which
value of these inputs should I register
and then on the output side how many
outputs should I register this is really
important because most likely if you
have
an arbitrary value on the input side
um you can like break it down into well
you could keep it as just one output put
the entire value that you have on the
input side minus fees onto one single
output but then most likely there is not
going to be a single other user that has
exactly this weird output amount that is
just your inputs on because that's again
something arbitrary right you you
register whatever amount you have in
your wallet and
that's difficult to plan or prepare
um so in many cases it makes sense to
split up the value that you have in this
coin join into multiple outputs
um and but the big question is no no
that the client has the ultimate control
and responsibility over which amounts do
you want to register on the output side
well for the first time we have to ask
of them which amount do I want
especially because you don't know the
amounts that other users will register
and if the complexity is now on the
client side and not dictated by the
server each client might behave
differently and then the question of how
do we coordinate in this somewhat
anarchic set of of users that just can
do whatever they want and that was an
extremely extremely difficult challenge
to solve and
way more difficult than the cryptography
stuff that was the easy part in
hindsight this is the real [__] like how
does the client choose which inputs to
select and how many inputs and then how
does the client choose or by the way
that when you register your inputs you
do not know the inputs that other users
register because that's happening right
now and in the future and so you don't
know how many how many inputs are there
what's the value of them necessarily uh
and then same with the outputs and if
you want to register your output at this
point you know which inputs have to use
have other users registered but you
still don't know which outputs will they
register and which values will those
outputs have
um and so this again very complex
problem and our initial solution to this
is to define a set of standard
denominations that are very carefully
chosen
um so these are powers of two powers of
three and powers of ten in the one to
five series uh plus multiple thereof so
there's I think 97
standard denominations that we have
defined and the client prefers to
register these standard denominations
we even further reduce the amount of
denominations based on the value of
which inputs are currently registered
um and so this basically means we have
somewhat of a shelling Point uh the coin
join clients Wasabi clients will will
behave somewhat similarly depending on
the current coin join round
um but still with a lot of Randomness
introduced so if the same client will
behave differently even if you would see
the exact same coin join on the input
side The Chosen outputs would be
different the next time around because
there's a computer Randomness introduced
um so this again to sum up gives the
client a lot of flexibility and he can
choose to get these standard
denominations uh and a lot of people
will choose the same standard
denominations so we have classical Anon
set the same denomination like 0.1
Bitcoin
um is going to be represented like 20
times in this transaction
so we have a classical anonymity set but
the really cool thing is contrary to any
other coin Zone implementation in the
past now you the client can choose which
denominations he has and he can easily
move in between denominations within the
same round
and so well how do you know that this
user has a 0.2 Bitcoin output or two
times 0.1 Bitcoin output
and that that is both that both could be
the case so you don't just get privacy
within the same denomination you get
privacy across these standard
denominations
um because they have what's known as a
low hemming weight it's very easy or
very efficient to decompose into these
standard denominations and so what we
found that regardless of which input
value you have in most cases you can
express this input value minus fees in
less than eight outputs so like six
outputs four outputs
um any input value can be broken down
into these which means for most cases
you will not create an output that is a
non-standard denomination right so
something that's that's not this powers
of two powers of three Etc
um meaning that every output is a
standard denomination
um which means you at least get that
privacy across the difference
denominations and then most likely other
users will also have chosen the same
denomination by random chance and then
you get the classical anonymity set
within the same denomination
um the end result in any case though is
that we have very little change
basically no change and we could Define
change in two ways first the worst kind
of change is a non-standard denomination
so something that's not the power of 2 3
or 10. and and or it might be a standard
denomination but it's the only output in
this coin join with this denomination
um that might happen as well very rarely
and especially for whales
um because ultimately this is a
liquidity problem and Size Matters and
if you're a whale with like a thousand
Bitcoin and you're swimming in the
transaction with tiny goldfish you know
that each have like 0.1 Bitcoin well
you're gonna get a change that's like
990 in Bitcoin
um and you're changed and can it's going
to be a non-standard denomination and
it's going to have one Anon set and
there's only one input that could have
paid for such a large output and it's
the real input
um but unless you're the richest guy
which like in wasabi terms is if you
have less than 10 Bitcoin you're going
to be one of the small fish swimming
around in this pool of standard
denominations
um
one final addition to say is contrary to
Wasabi 1.0 and a bit more similar to
Samurai now we have predetermined
standard denominations that do not
change across rounds
remember in 1.0 each round has a
slightly lower equal denomination than
before that's why it's quote unquote not
a standard denomination just in that
equal denomination for this round
um but with one with 2.0 because we have
the standard denominations when you
remix so when you register a coin join
output which is a standard denomination
and you put that on the input side of
the next coin join you're going to have
a standard denomination on the input
side of the coin join as well
and and not just is it a standard
denomination most likely another user
from another previous coin join realm
registered the same standard
denomination so you have anonymity set
on the input side as well right and and
this means now we generate an anonymity
set and ambiguity across denominations
on both the input and the output side
and we completely eliminate the the need
to create a non-standard output
um which which would be a non-private
change
yeah go ahead Seth uh Max I was a great
rant I enjoyed it but Seth go ahead
yeah sure I can I can jump in so
I think an interesting point that you
mentioned at the end is that
I think you'll describe it as a change
elimination protocol but there actually
is change or just including it in the
mix and hoping that there's enough
similar outputs to cover it so it's kind
of like an in-between of the
previous approach and the current one
and normally changes is not included
which is is definitely interesting um I
think the main question that I have is
because all of the amount decisions are
shifted to client-side Rhythm
coordinator side how can a client be
sure that it will gain a reasonable
amount of privacy a reasonable an onset
when it goes to mix if it doesn't know
what the other output amounts within the
mix are how am I supposed to know that
my client won't choose output amounts
that are
not shared by anyone else in that mixing
round and thus gain very very little
traditional anonymity and then I guess
the the second question would be
how do you actually measure the
anonymity provided by that idea of
inputs not necessarily being mapped by
Outlet by amount to outputs and thus
theoretically gaining the anonymity set
of every input that could have included
that output denomination
potentially is there a way that you're
measuring that or showing that to be
provably effective I know that big
numbers sound good to people but I would
love to hear more on how you're actually
measuring and ensuring that that
approach actually provides privacy and
isn't just obfuscation through
numbers
go ahead
yeah yes guys I had a point on uh Seth's
Point around uh change change inclusion
in in Wabi Sabi
um it's toxic change elimination and so
ultimately you're still getting changed
back to your wallet right it's just that
that change is not deterministically
linked to your initial original input
that you consumed in that coin join
transaction right this is the key itself
it could be like in the exact example
that Max gave at the end if you have by
far the largest input you would have a
change output that is deterministically
linked back to you I mean there's no 100
100 there's no denial it's
deterministically linked and this is the
exception of a lonely whale like a
really big whale you know swimming alone
in a big pond of goldfish that whale for
sure is going to have to coin join
multiple times until that deterministic
link of the change is gone because the
change output is a standard change
output from the 79 denominations that
wabi-sabi offers in the in the coin join
implementation so it's pretty
interesting because it kind of makes you
want to revisit the definition of change
and I think a lot of people in Bitcoin
they assume that change has to be
deterministically linked to your
original input that you consumed in a
transaction right
but it doesn't have to be in in
wabi-sabi like you're you're literally
if you're not a whale of only whale uh
you're literally breaking that that uh
that State of Affair for a change I
guess and now change is part of that big
pond of oh maybe it's linked to that
input or that output and and it's very
hard to know
um and yeah you're assigning it a
probabilistic link instead of a
deterministic certain link and that's
that's pretty uh pretty powerful and
pretty interesting that that yeah that's
the key point
yeah and one I think my main concern
with an approach like that is that it
doesn't
give a shorty to the user of what they
can expect of privacy on the other end
of mixing and that's one of the things
that I think is very beneficial in the
approach that's taken by Samurai wallet
is because you know change will be
excluded at the beginning and you know
that that change will be set aside not
easily spendable Etc you know the
Privacy you're gaining from every round
of mixing you do you know what kind of
entropy you're gaining you know what an
on-site you're gaining no matter what
there are no exceptions that is what
happens but when you introduce this
approach you're ultimately introducing
the risk of potentially not having
strong privacy on the other side and it
being determined by multiple different
factors which I think is dangerous
because people think okay I mixed my
funds they're private now but they might
be they might not be you're saying that
based on the amounts that normal people
will be mixing they probably are but
it's dangerous when we talk privacy
tools that don't guarantee privacy when
the thing that's supposed to have
privacy happens and instead makes it
reliant on other factors most of which
are outside of a user's control
and yeah I mean these are all great
points by the way the isolation strategy
is is interesting in some ways but if
you look at wabi-sabi again you said you
talk about privacy guarantees
um and this is whereisabi introduced a
much more conservative scoring that a
nonsense which is a non-scoring a
non-score basically if you look at so an
onset is you know you have one
denomination output of 0.1 BTC if in a
coin joint transaction there are 10 of
these 0.1 btcs you have an onset of 10
right
um and with wabi-sabi because you have
you can register multiple inputs and
multiple outputs in a given coin join
without linking
input to input or output to output and
of course input to Output
um the wallet itself is going to compute
a local score to tell the user hey this
is the level of privacy you get and it's
always much more conservative than the
announce set so a non-set is kind of a
it's a public on-chain metric that
anybody can compute if they look at a
transaction at a coin drone transaction
right anybody can agree on a given set
on a given a non-set however a non-score
is client specific
and so this is where you're getting that
privacy guarantee because the client is
going to tell you hey that a non-score
you got for that output which is
non-standard because you're a lonely
well is not good enough in terms of of
privacy guarantees coin join again
right until you're getting to that score
where you're gonna get that nice green a
hundred percent privacy score on your
Wasabi 2.0 client which says okay now
you have sufficient and non-score
um to meet your privacy goals and your
and and Achieve strong privacy
guarantees so in that sense you get
those privacy guarantees it's just a
different scoring and I think a lot of
users don't truly understand what a
non-score is we have those discussions
in the team it's like oh well how do we
explain the non-score what does it mean
like can you show us a formula to to
just put it on Twitter and and explain
it really well and simply and the fact
of the matter is it's very complicated
uh it's still being worked on improved
on and making you know made more robust
but uh it it gives you a a different
view on on privacy guarantees but are
very strong
so if I can hop in really quick Seth I
actually wanted to respond to the
comment about change partitioning in
transaction zero uh versus doing it in
the coin join itself
um I think this is a complete fallacy
and it makes absolutely no difference in
terms of privacy in the coin join
whatsoever peeling change off before the
coin join or during the coin joint
because just think about the links that
you are trying to protect
um between that change and mixed outputs
what you're trying to protect is a link
between that change output and the
actual mix outputs
now if we look at Wasabi 1.0
um instead of wabi-sabi and compare that
to Samurai
what is the information you glean from
observing the change output you learn
the input that it came from
you learn the first mixed transaction
that that input participated in
and there is no linkage between the
derived mixed denomination outputs and
that change whatsoever unless you
actually spend them together in the same
transaction
now in the case of Samurai you have
transaction zero which breaks things up
into mixed denominations
and then breaks the change off but you
still see transparently on the
blockchain exactly which first mixed
transaction
each of those mixed denomination outputs
go into with no link between the change
in the case of Wasabi 1.0 you see that
the change output was created and you
know a certain number of mixed
denominated outputs were created in that
transaction but you still do not see any
linkage between those specific mixed
denomination outputs and the change
output
so in terms of breaking the change off
before the coin join in the coin join it
makes absolutely zero difference in
terms of anonymity or privacy like
whatsoever
yeah it's a good point I think the
bigger deal is is separating it in a way
that's not spendable by the user by
default rather than that it's peeled off
in TX here or unless in the coin Jordan
round yeah I think that's a good point
yeah
as well it's just that even if you have
a non-standard change output if it is
small enough and if there's enough other
users with similar input or output
values then you still get at least some
ambiguity it might not hold up to
rigorous scrutiny you know but at least
it's not as easy as you know looking at
the largest input and the largest output
um it does become non-trivial uh to to
do it
um in the sense of you just looking at a
block Explorer at least the current
technology
uh yeah if I may I would just want to
recap a little bit like all of these
four different implement the
implementations that we talked about now
so like the first three they had this
problem where you had to you know have a
certain denomination and if you had
below it you basically had to
consolidate multiple inputs together and
reveal the common input ownership
to be able to participate in the coin
join or if you had more than the
denomination you had a toxic change now
what happened with 2.0 well each input
is now registered separately so there is
no way to even for the coordinator to
know which inputs actually belong
together or are coming from the same
user so that is already like a huge
breakthrough in Bitcoin like privacy
now then also the fact that like there's
basically usually no change so we had to
go to like a a philosophical discussion
uh internally in wasabi about like what
is actually toxic change so you know is
there a difference between a change and
a toxic change
like toxic changes probably the one that
is deterministically linkable
but what if there's a change but it's
not deterministically linkable it's just
like probabilistically linkable
so for example in a vb2 coin join
um it would mean that there is a bunch
of inputs different sizes there is a
bunch of outputs also and you have one
of the small outputs in there
and there is no other equal denomination
in this Conjuring round but it's kind of
impossible for you to know which input
did it come from or if it is connected
to some other output
so
we could call it the change
but it's at least not toxic change
anymore
so that is also like pretty darn good
the only thing I'd argue is just that
it's not not toxic it's just potentially
less toxic it's
it's again when there's not a guarantee
of what level of privacy you're gaining
with that yes there may not be a 100
deterministic link but if there's a 95
probability that these are linked
together
it it's essentially the same to a bad
actor like Jane Alice's who are more
than happy to make guesses and jump in
on that on that front but I mean Seth
you you cannot say
ever that anything is a hundred percent
deterministically like unlinked that
there is no probability of analysis like
you cannot make claims like that in a
coin joint because you are ultimately
assuming honest behavior from all the
other participants like half of your
round in Whirlpool could just be chain
analysis with a modified client keeping
a hundred different disconnected outputs
registered pretending to be separate
wallets like you cannot honestly make a
claim that any type of coin join system
is perfectly like obfuscated or
perfectly deterministically unlinked
like that because you cannot guarantee
that honest behavior from other
participants like that it's literally
impossible like claims like that are are
just dishonest
Wasabi 2.0 research
um because the the question of how do we
do a coin join coin selection that works
when you don't know how other users
behave it's like I cannot overstate how
[__] difficult of a problem this is
like this is crazy this is absolutely
insane
um and so we're we're definitely a bit
lost here um and it took us quite a
while to get even a solution that was
somewhat decent uh this is all
documented in GitHub nopara 73 sake uh
where we did some uh simulations of of
coin drone users giving them different
uh client-side codes to to run with and
there was a lot of experimentation on
things like for example which should be
the standard denominations
um and then how should we choose among
them especially then considering that
um
it is very easy to break any input
amount into just private outputs if if
you create many many outputs
um that's a very easy solution to get a
lot of privacy
um but the big problem is that this
comes at a cost because we're dealing
with block space here and if you create
too many outputs then you consume you're
in it's like an infinite blow up of the
utx all set that that cannot scale
um so at at some point it makes
Financial sense to create a non-standard
amount change
um and so the the but the crucial thing
that we learned is this depends on the
size of the coin join on the number of
inputs
um even the current like rather
optimized coin selection algorithm that
we have
it works really badly if there's less
than 50 inputs there's less than 50
inputs you're going to have a lot of
standard denominations with just one
anonymity set and a lot of non-standard
change outputs uh like or like
non-standard amounts on the output side
also before an anonymity set and only
when you reach more than 50 inputs do
you really start to see high efficiency
in the sense that there is no standard
denomination that does not have an onset
and that there is not a single
non-standard denomination output either
um and so that's why now in wasabi 2.0
as we're running in production we have a
minimum input amount of 150. if there's
less than 150 input the coin join does
not continue
and this means that there is actually
some decent Assurance of privacy that
that we get just based on the the the
simulation analysis that we did and
given the quite substantially larger uh
increase from like at 50 inputs it
starts getting okay and at 150 Bitcoin
inputs it's it's very good and we can go
even higher you know 300 400 600 inputs
and at that level uh the assurance that
you have at least some anonymity set for
basically any denomination again unless
you're the mega whale is rather High
um but still regardless the client makes
this privacy analysis after the coin
joint transaction so as the coin runs
finalized signed confirmed on the
blockchain then the client goes through
and sees okay so what level of anonymity
set did I actually gain and that depends
on what was the anonymity set of your
inputs and uh the anonymity score sorry
and then what's the anonymity set of the
outputs that gets reduced into the
anonymity score at a very conservative
rate so in many cases the coin join
robot is going to say okay this is not
yet good enough we have to register this
coin into the next round for example
because it was the lonely whale right so
these quote-unquote privacy flaws are
gracefully handled client-side because
the wallet will not spend that
non-private change output of the whale
it would tell them hey this is not yet
private
can you break down the Anon score and
the way that you actually measure that
anonymity provided anymore I know Tebow
said that it's a little bit hard you
know been struggling to kind of
make that quantifiable but I'd love to
hear more about how you measure that
because that's the core of how you
decide if an output should be mixed more
or can be spent or can't be spent Etc
can I take this one yeah good luck
yeah so I mean it's a very difficult
topic this anode score and it is like
something we have to say already at this
point it is only the best possible way
of calculating the privacy of the people
like the uh for these coin joints for
the specific outputs
um like it's just the best one that we
have
um and it's kind of like a modified
version of anon set so well just to go
back a little bit uh there's kind of
like three so-called privacy guarantees
of Wasabi 2.0 and napara he actually
went and created an awesome article
explaining these three privacy
guarantees so one is that the more
inputs there are there is like the
likelihood that there is going to be
multiple uh like equal denominations
it gets higher and higher and like Max
said when it gets like 150 inputs or
like 300 or something like that it's
going to be like a very very likely that
there's going to be multiple equal
amount uh for equal amounts for like all
of the denominations now that is good
that provides us an onset that is one
privacy guarantee now there's also like
the
um the fact that now in wasabi you
cannot really know uh how many inputs
that this user has and into how many
outputs did it break did he break the
amount into and you know all of these
kind of nuances like it makes it really
really difficult to try to analyze uh
Wasabi conjoin transactions because
there's kind of like this possibility of
you breaking down your amounts in many
different ways so you don't really know
it it's it's kind of like another way of
kind of like making it difficult for any
analyzer to figure out like what really
happened over here now the third one
which is not really like a guarantee you
know it's just like
a practical thing that we've noticed is
that it is very difficult to try to even
create a probability table for a coin
joint transaction as large as Wasabi 2.0
upon joints like if you have 300 inputs
and 300 outputs just trying to calculate
some kind of a you know doing coin joint
Sudoku and trying to figure out
which inputs could have gone or broken
down into which outputs or consolidate
into like you know all of the
possibilities that is just something
that we have not with our Hardware being
able to like even do
so well kycp doesn't either on margins
actually they just go run it yourself
because it's so computationally
expensive
yep so it is like you know it's even if
you have these amounts that like as long
as you are not the big whale and a
lonely whale in wasabi 2.0 conjoin
transaction it is going to be a very
crazy hard to figure out the input like
input input linkage input output linkage
or output output linkage now there is
extent then some claims about like okay
how about the uh like post coin join
activity but we can go into that later
but by itself like now in the Wasabi
wallet 2.0 coin joints there is a bunch
of these so-called like privacy
guarantees so we have the traditional
addon set but we have much more things
on top of it
and actually I think especially when we
want to focus on change in coin joints
it's it's important to look at the the
entire user journey and where if you
just hinted it in some regards what
about post links right so the entire
user journey is you have an arbitrary
amount input value and and maybe that's
not going to be enough as the minimum
denomination that the coordinator
dictates in in Whirlpool or Wasabi 1.0
for example right so so then you have a
problem and and you're excluded
um but uh so you have to consolidate
multiple input coins in the same coin
join transaction or tx0 transaction
which reveals common input ownership at
least to the coordinator with Wasabi 1.0
and to the entire blockchain with with
tx0 in Whirlpool
um which isn't great right and but then
okay great you you're now in the coin
Zone you get your private output amount
of a standard denomination but now you
want to make a payment and the big
problem is well the payment the merchant
one is an arbitrary amount and it's very
likely not that standard denomination
that that you have so you have to
consolidate multiple inputs to make a
payment
and also you you were going to have to
create a change output because the
Merchant's payment output is is not the
value of your inputs
um and then if the coordinator dictates
certain input and output values in the
coin join this means that you cannot do
a coin that you cannot do the payment
inside the coin join right like for
example in wasabi 1.0 uh like no but no
Merchant wants to get exactly
0.1123 or something and in in Whirlpool
well you couldn't even select multiple
inputs right the coordinator says you
can only have one input
um and no Merchant wants to get the
exact pool denomination so this means in
1.0 Wasabi and in Samurai you would have
to make single user payment transactions
but single user transactions are
horrible because we've revealed common
input ownership and so now if you need
to consolidate multiple standard
denomination coin join outputs in your
single user payment transaction you just
revealed common input ownership right
and then you have the merchants payment
out like output and your change output
well no the merchant knows that this is
your change output and an outside
Observer knows that well this is the
change output to a payment that was done
by a coin joint user
um and then you will most likely want to
get privacy back on the change output
right it's toxic after all uh so you
want to put it into a coin join well but
the problem is by definition you just
made a payment with a standard
denomination so the change output is
going to be less than that meaning you
cannot go back into the same
denomination coin join pool right let's
say in wasabi 1.0 you have you get a 0.1
output you make a
0.03 payment and you get your 0.07
change well that's 0.07 change cannot be
registered in the 0.1 pool meaning you
have to consolidate to get into decline
joint again
and that that sucks for privacy so uh
the the change output is is such a huge
problem not just inside conjurins but
also inside payments which cannot be
made inside the coin joins both because
of the entire idea of trying to prevent
change
um but here is where Wasabi 2.0 really
comes into shine like it just shows the
incredible benefit of of having flexible
uh or arbitrary amount of coin joints
um you can come in with any amount that
you just withdrew from an exchange or
whatnot and get only private outputs on
the output side and now you have a
multitude of different standard
denominations in your wallet after a
couple rounds of coins run and now if
you want to make a single user payment
transaction you can combine these
standard denominations very efficiently
to reach any arbitrary payment output
value with only a handful of inputs
right these standard denominations are
good for decomposing like breaking down
a large amount into many smaller amounts
but they're equally as efficient in
taking a bunch of small amounts and
adding them up to a precise large amount
and so with very few inputs you can make
any value payment
but still let's assume that you still
get a change output back
um well the change output is going to be
lower than the standard denomination on
your input side but in 2.0 it doesn't
matter because you can register as low
as 5000 satoshis on the input side
regardless of what amount it is so a
payment change output can directly be
registered in the coin join and it it
can be registered together with private
outputs that you have right so you can
combine one or two non-private change
outputs together with three or four
private coin join outputs which means
now even though one or two coins of
yours are revealed on the input side all
of your other coins that you have on the
input side are private and so even an
outside Observer who might know that
this specific change coin belongs to you
he does not know which other inputs you
have and therefore the value of the
inputs that you have and if you don't
know the value of the inputs that you
have it's going to be even more
difficult to find out which output
values do you actually have
um so ultimately with 2.0 we have a much
smoother user experience that is that is
faster and especially cheaper and more
private where you can get any arbitrary
input value and even after making a
payment you can register the change
without any issue in the next coin joint
I want to make an attempt to uh Steel
Man assess concerns because I'm not sure
he's gotten like a satisfactory answer
yet so
um if I get if I'm getting this correct
the concern is that change when it's not
fully eliminated that it doesn't have
um another person of the same standard
amount in the round to blend in with
um
you know are users getting a false sense
of privacy where they're assuming that
their coins have been made private but
it's there's no guarantee so I think the
Seth is saying that
Samurai provides you guaranteed privacy
because you get a predictable five a
non-set or score
um
when you complete in a given round
so there's some nuances to that
but they can't guarantee that though
they can provide a very high level of
probability but the only people that can
guarantee that are the actual
participants in a round
I mean even you know I think what the
point is is just on the blockchain
transaction in Samurai I know but I feel
it is important to really drive home
that point I mean that's true of
everything now it's true if Wasabi
wallet because Wasabi could be just as
easily yes it's Rich it's well that's a
debate of the different fee structures
but the point is like just the structure
of a coin join itself doesn't guarantee
that it's the participant set and their
behavior
I did focusing on the on-chained
footprint is more helpful here so that
we don't get into the weeds of civil
attacks though yeah there's a lot of
variables having to do with um with user
Behavior after they get their coins so
yeah just focusing on the coindalin
structure uh what Wasabi does here is
that if
you um claim an output for which there's
no matching amounts right to where let's
say I happen to pick .01 Bitcoin and for
some reason no other clients decided to
uh to pick outputs of that amount
my Wasabi client will say that I didn't
gain any privacy on this and for example
if you're a whale if you have a thousand
uh Bitcoins you get 990 Bitcoin change
it will also say you do not get any
privacy for this in which case you
really didn't because you're the whale
however
if you're not the whale if I'm actually
getting .01 and no one else happened to
get this
my client doesn't assign it as being
private however on the blockchain it
becomes
more private because
there's not a clear input that this
belongs to assuming there's like
clusters of input amounts around .01
so or lower amounts that can be combined
to add up to 0.01 so users will never
under mix
because they will always get the minimum
of the amount assigned to you
from equal amounts so if there's five
point zero one outputs then you get a
score of five if there's ten then you
get a score of 10. unless you have two
of them in which case it's lower
so you'll never get a false sense of
privacy it will always underestimate the
amount that you actually get
and are users prevented from spending
until they reach some
lower bound of that Anon score or how is
it actually handled for the user when
they're
mixing they don't gain the Privacy they
want what does that look like to the
user and how do you prevent users from
spinning those funds anyways because
they assume that they have privacy yep
so the way that appears in the client is
um a privacy percentage number uh so
we'll give you a private balance and a
non-private balance so your total
balance is one Bitcoin and only uh point
zero four or sorry 0.4 has been made
private then you have like a 40 privacy
progress and there's like a weighted an
on-score thing there but basically you
will be allowed to spend 0.4 Bitcoin
privately if you try to spend more than
that then it will alert you that a
previous uh sender or
uh or recipient via your change output
would know that you're combining uh or
that you're sending payments that they
would know about
yeah and also I just wanted to mention
like you know uh trying to steal man the
argument uh like you mentioned
previously crew uh it would be basically
that it would be crazy to say that you
cannot have privacy unless there is
anonymity set
that doesn't sound right you know there
can be definitely privacy without having
equal amount outputs
so
like all of these outputs that are
coming from Wasabi 2.0 coin join that
are not the whale output we are not
calculating like the client is saying
that yeah these are not private but in
practice if you look at the blockchain
level it is going to be crazy hard to
figure out any of the linkages but we
are being conservative on the client
we're still not considering that enough
we want to have all of these three
privacy guarantees kind of like met
before we keep it like an anal score
and again I just want to highlight of
how how incredibly difficult this
problem is uh and it's not just a
problem in general it's also a problem
in that specific application because
you're a local wallet that doesn't have
the entire blockchain transaction
history or or just the coin join
transaction history of of this
coordinator or maybe Associated
coordinators uh so if it's just an
extremely difficult problem and it needs
to be performant as well because this
runs on on everyday computers
um it's it's just super difficult uh
what what we have is well it works
obviously
um but it's it's for sure not perfect it
can 100 be done a lot better and there
has been by the way numerous
improvements to both the anonymity score
calculation as well as input and output
selection since Wasabi 2.0 was released
in in June 2022
um so this is this is definitely still a
living software and we're getting
numerous feedback improvements
um
yeah it's just difficult yeah maybe just
to kind of explain a little bit uh of
what is anon's core again like I forgot
to explain it in more detail previously
so imagine that you have a coin joint
round where you have let's say one you
have one of the outputs of one Bitcoin
and there is nine other outputs that are
also one Bitcoin so normally we would
consider that this your coin has an on
Set uh no yeah another set of ten right
so you know the thing is we could
previously say that with all of the
three old implementations because we had
this idea that like only like the user
will have only one of those equal
denomination outputs
that was the guarantee that kind of like
what enabled all of these
implementations to somewhat of at least
use and on set as an estimation of how
private did their output get there is
nine other outputs that are equal amount
and each of the outputs are owned by
different people
now with 2.0 that is not true anymore
so there can be that you might have
let's say two of those one Bitcoin
outputs instead of just one
so what would be then your Anon set well
it is again for each of the inputs and
also for each of the outputs that you
have like these one Bitcoin outputs and
on set is 10 but
because we cannot know if all of the
other eight outputs are also coming from
different people we have to be
conservative so there is certain
calculation of like how we don't like
the unknown score is a conservative
version of anon set so instead of like
you having one of those one Bitcoin
outputs
we don't give an Anon set of 10 we give
let's say as an example an unknown score
of four
because we assume that multiple of these
outputs might be actually from the same
user not all from Individual like
different individuals
so that is kind of like Anon score
so whenever like we have in a wallet now
we have Anon score targets when the user
starts a wallet he has to choose from
different profiles and their profiles
have a certain amount of like Anon score
that they are targeting and
automatically the whenever the
like the coin joint rounds succeed in a
way that it they actually do get this
traditional Anon set we make a
conservative calculation from that and
then we kind of like show it for the
user that hey you got privacy
so we are not even calculating or
counting into our like privacy
calculation the fact that it's like
computationally just hard to figure out
like all the possibilities of how the
linkages could go in this coin join
we're not counting on this like
um being able to break down the amounts
into multiple different ways we're being
like ultimately very very conservative
even like
well more conservative than Anon set in
the calculation of privacy
and actually this made me Interest
realize that every other coin Zone
implementation doesn't really address
this problem either
um joint Market does not give any
privacy scoring or anonymity scoring at
all if I understand it correctly
um they just cycle through mixed steps
but but at random basically
um if I understand correctly Samurai
looks at how many hops are you away from
tx0 but this approach really works if
you want to input one output in the coin
join which again has a lot of block
space deficiency downsides and so Wasabi
1.0 was really the first coin join or
the first wallet that implemented the
concept anonymity sets entirely
um and that's why it was very specific
to Wasabi 1.0
um and 2.0 change a lot of things and uh
that's why we felt the need to to
upgrade the the anonymity scoring um
yeah but but again hey guys this is
Uncharted Territory this is really
complex and nobody dealt with it in the
past
um so the we have we kind of opened
Pandora's box with that idea of
client-side coin join the lecture on the
output side
um
but the cool thing is now that that
allows us to add Randomness client-side
like I know exactly like a samurai or
workflow client is going to behave it
has one input one output right it's
always the same there is no ambiguity in
how the client chooses its denominations
versus even in 1.0 Wasabi I know that if
if a user had like one Bitcoin input she
got a 0.1 a 0.2 and a 0.4 and the point
would be change and I know how the
client behaved it was very deterministic
Behavior
um 2.0 Wasabi completely obliterates
this idea every
at the the number of inputs that are
selected has a Randomness the which
inputs are selected as Randomness uh how
many outputs you select has Randomness
which output denominations use rules has
Randomness
um so yes this makes it more ambiguous
you cannot say in the in the like right
now you cannot say how the next coin run
is gonna end up like what are the equal
amounts there you you don't know
um
um but well that's that's somewhat bad
if you want to plan well and if you want
to know exactly the result that you're
going to get you're not going to get
that for something 2.0 but neither does
the adversary have that advantage over
you as well because of the adversary of
the Observer knows exactly how you
behave
well that's bad but if there's computer
generated Randomness in how you behave
that is a big nightmare for the attacker
yeah now uh thanks everyone for that I
we're getting down to I can only be on
for another five minutes so I wish we
could keep this conversation going on
longer to be honest it's been a great
discussion but if we want to kind of go
around the table and go a final wrap up
from all the speakers if you want to
bring up anything that you're working on
or where people can follow you to keep
up with your work or anything that
you're working on I'll kick it over to
you guys maybe we'll start with Tebow
and then we'll kind of go Tebow Vlad Max
Seth wraith and then crew
yeah sure thing thanks for hosting us it
was a really good chat
um I mean I would say just give it a try
try the software try you know Wasabi 2.0
try Samurai try doing market and make up
your own opinion of it
um and keep digging it's a deep rabbit
hole
yeah so I just want to say that this was
objectively the best Twitter spaces
conversation I've ever participated in
it was incredible I want to thank you
all for joining this it was just
everything I've ever wanted to know on
the topic and explained what nuances and
not in absolute terms not with claims
that are unrealistic and marketable
this was just incredible I don't care to
see where you can follow me and whatever
I I want to tell you guys that this was
very good and it just saddens me when I
think that we're gonna go back to
Twitter and we're gonna return to
marketing terms and presenting stuff
that maybe cannot be explained properly
within the limits of a tweet and it's
gonna lead to a lot of arguments and
people are gonna choose their Wallet not
on the basis of their technical merits
but on the basis of their ideological
inclinations and they will just go for
the one that speaks in a way that
appeals to what they're searching for in
a privacy wallet so that's unfortunate
but this was really great and I wish
thousands of privacy wallet users would
listen to this and make their own
opinion
and thanks for for hosting this I agree
it really was a excellent conversation
um
I I just want to highlight again that
this is such a like we're at The Cutting
Edge Of The Cutting Edge and it really
is is an incredibly complex problem and
the problem that I think all of us were
ignorant I mean even I was ignorant
during the Wasabi 1.0 days
um the the
nuances and the complexities of this
problem
it didn't occur until you actually get
that opportunity of client-side amount
organization it's it's
so this is this is going to be Decades
of research in the making
um and uh that's for one extremely
encouraging but it's it's also a bit
scary uh because I know for a certainty
that what we have currently with Wasabi
2.0 or even with 2.0.3 or wherever we're
at now
um it is anything but perfect and we we
really really need to take a lot of Care
on on figuring this out uh it's and it's
going to require a lot of effort from a
lot of smart people
um and yeah good conversations like this
or hopefully a spark to to keep those
types of conversations going
um
beyond that what we have now is I think
good enough looking at the blockchain I
think the results are
cool
um and to to think that it can get even
better in the future is is what keeps me
working in the space
um yeah especially when I say thanks to
Seth uh for coming here
um that was courageous and good good
that we uh you know got some some good
and harsh questions and uh and some
insights on how samurai Works uh that's
great
um
yeah and also thanks for uh Shinobi with
his surprise appearance uh he was quite
instrumental actually in in in seeding
these ideas uh you know he was a big
part of of adding multi-denomination to
Wasabi 1.1
um that uh again that kind of
kick-started this entire thing so uh big
thanks to him he's been quite
instrumental in the research
yeah so uh thank you and let's keep
building
yeah I think just for me uh mostly was
here just to listen and learn and engage
and get some questions answered so thank
you to the Wasabi wallet folks who are
willing to jump on you know there's
always a lot of vitriol between
different privacy tools in the space
unfortunately
um it's not something that I'm a fan of
or engage in I don't think but it's good
to have these open honest nuanced
discussions in a format that like Vlad
said is not uh not character limited
because that that only leads to bad
things usually
um so yeah thankful for the time
thankful for the Insight um and fully
looking forward to learning more trying
to investigate find out what's good find
out what makes sense
um and ultimately I want privacy for
everyone I don't want it to be bound by
a specific wallet or anything like that
so if the tools work I'm excited but
definitely want to learn more about
wabi-sabi play around with Wasabi wallet
you don't know
um and yeah learn a little bit more so
thank you all for engaging thank you for
all the information uh thank you
everybody who jumped in and listened
today
well everyone who's been here uh
listening and asking questions and
discussing this matter I think it's
really really important like it's kind
of Reckless for bitcoiners to who
advocate for a lot of like
self-serverity things to not care about
privacy and I'm really sad that to kind
of see that you know the the Privacy
discussion in this space is usually
really like just crazy stupid uh you
know it's mostly like marketing and not
being honest with the uh the pros and
cons of each Pro each project and I
think it would be really valuable for us
to try to strive for that I mean there's
definitely things to improve in both
projects we should just be honest about
those facts and discuss them
but yeah thank you very much for
everyone
yep thank you the Bitcoin magazine and
for uh Seth for coming in with this
thoughtful questions
um the only thing I have to uh to push
and encourage people is to go look at a
wabi-sabi coins when transaction on the
blockchain because I think that like
when you actually see it with your own
eyes it starts to make sense uh kind of
like the depths of the Privacy that
you're getting
um when you kind of like scratch your
head I need a cup of coffee to try and
figure out where any where any uh input
or output goes so that's all for me
thanks everyone I want to thank all the
speakers for coming up and discussing
this it's been a great conversation and
it was on a truly an honor to moderate
this you guys made my job very easy by
the uh the nuance and depth of questions
and concerns that you guys all brought
up uh we hope to continue this
conversation down in Miami May 18th to
the 20th at the Bitcoin conference if
you haven't already gotten your tickets
already you can use code Satoshi to save
10 on your tickets down to the
conference uh but yeah thank you
everyone else for coming up and uh
discussing this and uh we will catch you
guys uh very soon have a good one
everyone bye